<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to a paper intitled, Reflections on the Prince of Orange's declaration</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11927181</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11927181</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to a paper intitled, Reflections on the Prince of Orange's declaration</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51053:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51053:1"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to a Paper, Intitled, <hi>Reflections on the Prince of</hi> Orange's <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT ſeems a ſtrange piece of Arrogance that any man ſhould reflect on a Declaration, becauſe it does not begin as he would have it; that is, with a Manifeſtation of our Clandeſtine League with <hi>France,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by and Army of <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> together with our <hi>Papiſts, Iriſh,</hi> and other Mercenaries, might eſtabliſh Popery in <hi>England.</hi> The Reflector ought to have conſidered, that a Clandeſtine League, tho' it may be very notorious to its Exiſtence and Effects, may likewiſe be very difficult to prove, according to the meaning of the Word Clandeſtine. But that there is ſuch a one, we have the Teſtimony of the King of <hi>France,</hi> in a Memorial delivered to the States of <hi>Holland;</hi> and though it has been ſince diſowned by our Court, and Mr. <hi>Skelton</hi> upon it committed to the Tower; his ſhort Confinement, and ſudden Advancement to a Regiment, ſhews that his Diſgrace was but a trick of State: It is alſo an inconſequential way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, that becauſe the Prince does not begin his Declaration with it, therefore there is no ſuch League, things of that high conſequence being eaſier and better carried on by ſecret Meſſages than Writing under Hand and Seal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his ſecond Reflection, he tells us the Prince had needed leſs Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, if he had pretended only to have come to deliver the King from Evil Counſellours, and to ingage him further in the intereſt of <hi>Europe;</hi> forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Prince does declare to us he comes for that end, tho' not ſingly, and brought over his Army to ſecure him from the Rage and Fury of thoſe Evil Counſellours. His next Quarrel is, that the Prince uſes the Stile, <hi>Of We and Us within His Majeſties Dominions;</hi> a thing, I believe, ordinary enough in Great Princes, when they ſpeak, or write, to their Inferiours. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is General of a great numerous Army, Admiral of a vaſt Fleet, State-holder to a High and Mighty Commonwealth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, too great to ſpeak in the Stile of a Private Perſon; ſo that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, Puniſhing, Commanding, Advancing, may very naturally fall within his Power. Nor is it any Crime to indeavour the calling of a Free Parliament, and ſettling the Nation, tho' by ways and methods unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual in our days, nothing being more frequent, in our Hiſtories, than for our Barons, with Arms in their Hands, to compel their Kings to call and heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to their Parliaments: But now there being a ſtanding Army of forty thouſand Mercenaries in the Land, it was grown a Crime to Petition for a Parliament, and a Folly to expect a free one, new Charters and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and a general nomination of incompetent Magiſtrates, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Election of Members for Parliament out of thoſe Hands, the Laws of the Land, and Memorial Cuſtom, had intruſted with them. According
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51053:2"/>to the new Scheme deſigned by thoſe Upſtart and Popiſh Counſellours, no man was to Elect, or be Elected for Parliament, that would not ingage, as far as in him lay, to take away the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt;</hi> nay, thoſe Wicked Counſellours prevailed yet farther upon His Majeſty; and he that pardoned ſo many of his Enemies, was not ſuffered to forgive his beſt Friends, and moſt Loyal Subjects a refuſal or excuſe in that particular.</p>
            <p>That the Prince will ſend back his Army, ſeems to ſome a ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption that he will not ſtay behind, ſince even our own lawful King thinks himſelf not ſafe without an Army of Mercenaries, in his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. From a ſtrain'd phraſe or two, <hi>Of We and Us, Require and Command,</hi> ſometimes uſed in his Declaration, to infer, That the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to make himſelf King of <hi>England,</hi> ſeems to all Rational Men a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Captions and Unſatisfactory way of arguing, and a very Unjuſt Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſt upon ſo great a Prince, ſince more than once, in expreſs terms, he Declares he has no deſign upon His Majeſties Crown or Perſon, ſo that all that Reproach falls to the Ground.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In his third Reflection, he tells us the Prince wants a clear Call, and that a Son againſt a Father, a Nephew againſt an Unkle, a Neighbour againſt a Neighbour, cannot be ſuch: That he is Son-in-Law, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to His Preſent Majeſty, gives the Prince a fair and juſt pretence to interpoſe in our Affairs; had he been a Foreigner as our Reflector terms him, it might have look'd like an intended Conqueſt; had he not been a Neighbour, it had been impoſſible for him to have afforded us this ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Aſſiſtance. But ſome think, that where attempts are made to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Catholick Religion, by a Conſpiracy, againſt the Laws that ſecure and eſtabliſh the Protenſtant Religion and the Teſt, that only can keep the Papiſts out of the Government: And to carry on this Conſpiracy the better, the old Charters are taken away under pretence of forfeiture, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; new ones granted, ſuch as might bring Elections within the power of thoſe Evil Counſellours; Papiſts upon the Bench, a Jeſuite in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; and whole Troops of them in the Army: 'Twas high time for a Proteſtant Prince, that had ſo near relation to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> to look about him, and chooſe rather to be Cenſur'd by our Reflector, and ſuch as he, for entering upon the Stage a little before his time, than be juſtly Reproach'd and Curs'd, to the end of the World, by all ſuch as love the Proteſtant Religion, and Ancient Government of <hi>England,</hi> for appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too late in their Defence. The Example of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, of <hi>France,</hi> may teach us how hard it is for a Proteſtant Prince to obtain his Right, where the Catholick Religion is Predominant; nor was the new Armour of Popery he put on, at laſt, ſufficient to defend the old Proteſtant againſt the Stab of a Jeſuited <hi>novitiate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His fourth Reflection acquaints us, the Proteſtant Religion is at once expos'd and hazarded, for if the King prevail what can the Prince of <hi>Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> ſort of Proteſtants expect at his hands; which are indeed, all ſorts of Froteſtants that I know of, for the <hi>Presbyterians, Independants, Phanaticks,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51053:2"/>Church of England men,</hi> are in his Army: 'Tis fair warning, and I hope God will give the Proteſtants Grace to make the right uſe of it: As for their changing Maſters, 'tis a <hi>Chimera</hi> of his own, and utterly Foreign to the Declaration he pretends to reflect upon. Leſt we ſhould forget, he reminds us with that admirable Demonſtration of, <hi>Iſay, that the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion is at ſtake;</hi> for which I heartily thank our Worthy Reflector, for tho' it be very true, we had not ſeen it in Print but for him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In his fifth reflection, he tells us that ſome Laws are better broken than kept, which will not be eaſily granted; tis indeed true, that ſome Laws were better be repealed than continued: But then they muſt be Nulld bu the ſame power they were conſtituted, and not by any part of it in contradiction to the whole.</p>
            <p>His inſtance is, that Chriſtianity could not have been introduc'd, had the <hi>Pagan</hi> Laws been Executed; by which Parallel he would warrant Popery to be the true Chriſtianity, and the Proteſtant the Healthen Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors; Laws for Idolatry cannot bind, therefore Laws againſt it cannot; a very ſtrange inference, and I allow that a Lawful Authority by exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their juſt Bounds, may act unlawfully, but the Legiſlative power cannot, ſince all over the World the Supream power ever was abſolute, be it in one or more. He ſays no Man is obliged to maintain a Religion that is not true, be it never ſo Legally Eſtabliſhed: So that is but ſaying the Proteſtant Religion is not true, and His Majeſty, notwithſtanding His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated ingagement, is no longer bound to protect it. For in the words of our Reflector 'tis an abſurdity and impiety to do ſo.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſixth thing conſiderable in our Reflector is, his defence of the Diſpenſing Power, and the uſe His Majeſty, ſeduc'd by his Evil Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, makes of it; which is no other than the ſetting aſide of all our Laws made for the ſecurity of the Proteſtant Religion; But ſure ſuch a Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive can never be Legally veſted in the Crown, which if admitted, were the deſtruction of all Law.</p>
            <p>Had thoſe Evil Counſellors only prevailed with His Majeſty, to have Diſpenſed with the Penalties inflicted on Catholicks and other Diſſenters, for ſerving God according to their Particular Conſciences, tho' perhaps contrary to Law, the matter had never been Complained of: But to put them into places of Higheſt truſt, to make one Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> another Preſident of the Council, a third Lieutenant General of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, a fourth a Judge; imploying numbers of them in the Army, Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a tranſgreſſion of the Law, which is certainly very dangerous, if not immediately, yet in its inevitable Conſequences, to the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Government, and therefore a miſchief remote only (as an Egg is from a Chicken) from the worthy reflectors <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges this Diſpenſing Power extends not to. And the particular Catholicks breaking the Law in theſe points, are without excuſe: For no Man is obliged in Conſcience to be a Judge, a Prieſt, a Miniſter, a Privy Councellor, a Courtier, or a Souldier in time of Peace; contrary to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51053:3"/>Laws of the Land. Nor do thoſe Laws deprive the King of the ſervice of any of his Subjects abſolutely; ſince all men if they pleaſe may Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate themſelves for imployment. If the High Commiſſion Court be at an End, <hi>Magdalem</hi> Colledge and the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> reſtored, we may in all appearance thank the honeſty and Caution of ſome of its worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the Noiſe of what our Reflector calls the Prince of <hi>Orange's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion; though ſome will ſay, a diſcent upon <hi>England</hi> made by a Prince of the Blood, Married to the Eldeſt Daughter of the preſent King, upon the invitation of many Lords both Spiritual and Temporal, and of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Gentry Commonalty of all Counties, might here deſerved a fairer Name. Nor ought any man to complain if his honeſt Neighbour break violently into his houſe at a time when his Family cry out Fire or Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Common obligation of humanity, and a due care of their own preſervation, exact no leſs of them. But this Paper is not intended for a vindication of the Prince, I will therefore return to my Reflector again, who undertakes for all good Proteſtants that they only refus'd to repeal the Teſt, by reaſon of the ſecurity it affords their Religion. As if they had caſt off all care of their Civil concerns, and were only intent upon Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affairs, ſo as to conſent to give his Majeſty a Majority of Papiſts in the Houſe of Lords; by which he might have two Negative Voices upon all Laws to be offer'd: and an Houſe of Pears ready to repeal the <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> Bill, and ſuch Statutes as any ways ſeem to incumber what Papiſts think his Majeſties Prerogative, of which they maintain the Diſpenſing Power to be an Eſſential part; and well they may, ſince it is the very power, by which he maintains them in their places and imployments: So that by leave of my worthy Reflector, the conſideration of Religion, tho' they are the principal, are not the only reaſons, that have determined all good Proteſtants to a Non-concurrence with His Majeſty in the repeal of the Teſt.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In his eighth Reflection he tells us, that Chappels are places of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo are the <hi>Turks</hi> Mosques, and the <hi>Jews</hi> Synagogues, yet no good Chriſtian but would be offended to ſee them multiply'd and encouraged, either in his own, or his Neighbours Country.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In his ninth he tells us, the King was content the Teſt ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main: I anſwer, theſe Evil Counſellours were not content the Teſt ſhould remain, but ſent their Regulators and other Agents, to threaten, promiſe, remove and change the Magiſtrates in all Corporations, in order to the procuring Members of Parliament, ſuch as were to enter the Houſe under ſolemn promiſes, and firm reſolutions, to take off the Penal Laws and Teſt, notwithſtanding all the weighty, nay, convincing Arguments they might meet with there to the contrary: A deſperate ſort of Senators, and fitter for <hi>Catalines</hi> Conſpiracies than an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament. Nor did theſe Evil Counſellours ceaſe to ſollicit even Knights of the Shire, till the general in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation their propoſals met with, together with the noiſe of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s preparations, frighted them from a further proſecution of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51053:3"/>enormous attempt. He ingeniouſly confeſſes the ſeizing of Charters to have been a fault, ſo there is no conteſt between us on that point; but he adds, That the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> has nothing to do with it; now others think him highly concern'd in it, for if according to Sir <hi>Thomas Moore, Rex Poteſt Juriper Parta mentum &amp; poteſt &amp; deſtrui;</hi> or according to the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of later times, a Parliament may make a Bill of Excluſion; a Prince that has ſo near a Relation to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> ought not to ſuffer any foul play in the calling together ſuch an Aſſembly as may null his Title, or preclude him of his Right to the Crown, in time to come. 'Tis true, the Council of ſeizing Charters was given in the laſt Kings Reign, and moſt of them then ſeized, but no man can deny but ſome have been condemned and ſeized in the Reign of his preſent Majeſty, and reſtored not till the univerſal apprehenſion of the aforeſaid Invaſion; ſo that we are promiſed a Free Parliament, only becauſe they cannot put one of their own framing upon us.</p>
            <p n="10">10. His tenth Paragraph needs no anſwer.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In his eleventh, he tells us there were but two Papiſt Judges, as if the Laws were not broken unleſs Judges were all Papiſts; or that Judges ſitting contrary to Law could give a Legal Sentence. Both theſe defects he ſuppoſes ſupplyed by the <hi>Diſpencing Power,</hi> a power ſufficiently baffled by thoſe Gentlemen of the lorg Robe of Councel for the Biſhops, and not defended by either Judges or Councel, on the other ſide; for which two of the Judges, <hi>Jones</hi> and <hi>Holloway,</hi> loſt their places on the Bench.</p>
            <p n="12">12, 13. His twelfth and thirteenth concern <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will leave them untouch'd, to the Gentlemen of thoſe Nations, who beſt underſtand, and are moſt ſenſible of the Oppreſſions they are under.</p>
            <p n="14">14. In his fourteenth, he pleads the Validity of the Kings Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, tho' that pretended <hi>Prerogative</hi> has been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd and baffled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> within theſe few years, and deſerted as ſuch by His late Majeſty; he affirms, that the King, as Head of the Church, might oblige the Biſhops to cauſe the Declaration to be read in the Churches, which if they had complyed with, in the Opinion of many good <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> they had precluded themſelves of their Votes in <hi>parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> againſt it; for with what forehead could they Vote againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, when they had cauſed it to be read in their Churches? An Act amounting to no leſs than maintaining; or owning, the <hi>Diſpencing Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. In his fifteenth, he allows the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> have in terms full of reſpect ſignified to the King their deep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret which all theſe things have given them, and their thoughts about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws</hi> as an expedient of Peace, but blames him, it ſeems, for doing all this ſo reſpectfully and privately, and would rather had it done by a Manifeſto, that ſome of the <hi>Princes,</hi> Friends might be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for delivering it, as Captain <hi>Lenham</hi> is for bringing over the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. He tells us next, the King has come up almoſt to <hi>Fagel</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was the Declaration of their Minds, <hi>viz.</hi> The Church of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51053:4"/>
               <hi>England</hi> Teſt, and Laws of Supremacy to remain; then urging the Kings Conceſſions, which may be obſerv'd to bear date only from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the <hi>Princes</hi> preparations for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. He tells us in his ſixteenth, that the <hi>Prince</hi> thinks a <hi>free Parliament</hi> to be the laſt and great Remedy for theſe Evils, but complaints theſe Wicked Counſellours are againſt it, for fear of being called to account, that they had preingaged Voices to take off the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Corporations and Burroughs, that ſo they might aſſure themſelves of the Members of <hi>Parliament;</hi> he allows the charge, but ſays what has all this to do with the King? No man ſay it has, and the <hi>Prince</hi> only requires the removal and puniſhment of thoſe Evil Counſellours in a Free <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Next our Reflector tells, that there never was a <hi>Parliament</hi> abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Free, but that Drink, Money, and other evil Arts, have had a great ſway in Elections: This is true, but no reaſon that we ſhould conſent to a General or Fundamental Corruption of our Elections, becauſe we cannot avoid ſome few and caſual ones. Then he would have had the <hi>Prince</hi> have deſired the King to have laid aſide thoſe Evil Counſellours, as if it were not Notorious, that the <hi>Princes</hi> diſlike of ſome men has been their ready way to preferment in our Court; and Embaſſadors for <hi>Holland</hi> have been, of late, choſen out of thoſe he has moſt averſion for, as if theſe Wicked Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours feared nothing ſo much as a good underſtanding between His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. In the Nineteenth he tells the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi>'s que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion concerning the Birth of the <hi>Prince of Wales,</hi> ſaying, That <hi>during the Queens pretended Bigneſs, and in the manner in which the Birth was managed, there have appear'd ſo many juſt and viſible ground of ſuſpicion, that not only the Prince himſelf, but all good Subjects in</hi> England <hi>do vehemently ſuſpect that the Pretended Prince of</hi> Wales <hi>was not born of the Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. Next our Reflector tells us, <hi>That the Prince ought to have writ to the King for a private ſatisfaction in his Matter, which the King would no doubt have given in the manner that all reaſonable men do when they are examined againſt themſelves.</hi> All men allow the imputation of ſuch an impoſture, to be a gret reflection on their preſent Majeſties: But ſome think they have in a great meaſure drawn it upon themſelves, by omitting to have thoſe witneſſes by, and thoſe Methods obſerved, that our Laws require to prove the Birth of a Legitimate Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> 'Tis not perhaps enough to ſay, that there were as many Witneſſes, and as good proof of it, as the Law exacts, ſtill the queſtion returns, why not the ſame perſons? a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal proof admits of no Equivolent.</p>
            <p>Our reflector will not deny, but there has been common ſame all over <hi>Europe,</hi> that this Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> was not Born of the Body of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; and common belief of it amongſt proteſtants; this of it ſelf were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make the next Heir to the Crown look about, and move every ſtone that the matter might be examined by impartial methods in a free
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51053:4"/>parliament, which is all that the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> aims at: for their proofs to the contrary, 'tis not to be expected they ſhould acquaint the World with them before the Tryal.</p>
            <p n="22">22. In his two and twentieth Reflection on the eighteenth Paragraph, where the Prince ſays, <hi>He was invited to this Expedition by many Lords, both Spiritual and Temporal, and many Gentlemen, and Subjects of all Ranks;</hi> Our Reflector is pleaſed to tell him he is miſtaken as <hi>Monmouth</hi> was. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe eminent Peers, Gentry and Commonalty of all ſorts that are already in his Camp, and ſuch as are going daily, as well Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as others; nor conſidering the great number of the Nobility that are in the Country and have not been examin'd, and that ſuch as were exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd here in Town, did no more than anſwer Not Guilty to the Charge of High Treaſon: So that there are more Nobility and Gentry with him than with his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>In his three and twentieth Reflection on the 19th and 20th Paragraph, where the Prince refers all to a free Parliament; our Reflector ſays it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to him, to refer other mens buſineſs; as if the <hi>Prince</hi> had no relation to the Crown: Then tells us we are already in poſſeſſion of what the <hi>Prince</hi> promiſes us, as if the Catholicks were all out of imployment, the Diſpencing power given up, no ſtanding Army, no apprehenſions of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> for redreſſing of Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of all kinds in being.</p>
            <p n="24">24. In the twenty fourth Reflection on the three laſt Paragraphs of the <hi>Princes</hi> Declaration, he tells us, <hi>The Prince has a manifeſt deſign upon the Crown, becauſe he ſummons the Nobility, Gentry and People of England to his Standard: And if ſo, who muſt ſtay with the King?</hi> To that may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, All ſuch as believe the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> has brought this Army, and intends to make War upon <hi>England</hi> to ſubdue it to his meer will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, trample all Laws, both Divine and Humane, under his Feet, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne his preſent Majeſty, and make himſelf King; they will ſtay and fight for him, or at leaſt to the beſt of their power, in ſome other manner aſſiſt and help him: On the contrary part, ſuch as believe the <hi>Prince</hi> means nothing of all this, but brought over his Army only the better to aſſiſt the Nobility, Gentry, and people of <hi>England,</hi> upon their earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and frequent ſolliciations, and reiterated complaints, in the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of the old Legal way of chooſing Members for <hi>Parliament,</hi> which by Illegal new Charters, on pretended forfeitures, was in a ready way to be for ever loſt, in reſcuing all the Laws of <hi>England</hi> from the devouring laws of a <hi>Diſpencing Power,</hi> in reducing <hi>Popery</hi> within thoſe bounds the Law has preſcribed it, which, like an Inundation, had ſo over-flowed its Banks, that our Religion and Government were in peril to be ſwallowed up by it; and finally, to redreſs theſe and all other grievances, if for theſe and no other ends or concerns, men think the <hi>Prince</hi> have landed here, ſuch men will take his part, eſpouſe his quarrel, and contribute to his ſucceſs: and in theſe caſes every man will judge for himſelf, as they did in our late Civil Wars.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51053:5"/>
            <p>Again, he charges the <hi>Prince</hi> with a deſign of Conqueſt; which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Prince</hi> himſelf diſclaims throughout his Declaration, and will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after diſown in all his Manifeſto's; but the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> who have ſo vigorouſly aſſiſted, and engaged themſelves with all their power and credit, to maintain him in this attempt, have aſſur'd us he left <hi>Holland</hi> under high and ſolemn proteſtations to the contrary. All this is, I hope, ſufficient to daſh the ſtrain'd inferences of an inconſiderable Reflector.</p>
            <p>As for that impudent Calumny of <hi>Perjury</hi> he indeavours to ſix upon the <hi>Prince,</hi> it needs no other refutation than a ſerious conſideration of the Charge it ſelf; his Words are, <hi>The Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>ſwore to the States of</hi> Holland <hi>never to be their State-holder, tho' it were offered him, and yet is now that very State-holder he ſwore never to be on any terms.</hi> Now let any reaſonable man conſider, whether it be poſſible a Wiſe State ſhould by an Oath given him, diſable the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> from being their State-holder, tho' Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and times ſhould ſo change, that their immediate preſervation and very exiſtence of their State ſhould require him to accept, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that Office. For his perſonal Reflections towards the latter end I think very Impertinent, and only fit to be buried in Contempt.</p>
            <p>Thus having followed my tedious Reflector through his twenty four Reflections, I take my leave of him, reſerving the <hi>Princes</hi> farther Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſome time when I ſhall be more at leiſure to write, and people willinger to read, than they can be under the preſent ſurprize, hourly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and continual anxiety, for the event of this Heroick Enterpriſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51053:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
